J. Peter Lesley Papers 1826-1898 Mss.B.L56
American Philosophical Society
J.P. Lesley Papers
1826-1898
Mss.B.L56
American Philosophical Society
7.75 Linear feet
After a brief career in the Congregational church, J. Peter Lesley (1819-1903) left the ministry in 1852 to work full-time as a geologist. Having gained experience in structural geology and stratigraphy with the First Pennsylvania Geological Survey (1836-1842), Lesley became an expert in the geology of coal, working for the Pennsylvania Railroad and other corporations and conducting some of the first systematic studies of the state's hydrocarbon resources. A long-time professor at the University of Pennsylvania, he was elected to the APS in 1856, serving variously as its librarian, secretary, and vice president, and he was selected as Director of the Second Pennsylvania Geological Survey (1875-1889). The Lesley Papers include letters to and from Peter Lesley and his wife, Susan on geology, coal and iron mining, abolition, educational reform, organized charity, and Unitarianism. The collection offers important insight into academic and applied geology in late 19th century Pennsylvania, the development of the coal and iron industries, as well as into the Lesleys' progressive social and intellectual milieu. It is divided into three series: Lesley's general correspondence, his correspondence with his brother Joseph, and microfilms of Lesley's research notes.
Lesley, Allen
Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903
Box 1-16
Scope and Contents note
Far more than the record of the professional activities of an important geologist, the J. Peter Lesley Papers reflect the intellectual and social lives of a prominent and politically progressive Philadelphian during the mid-19th century. Seen in the context of the expansion of one of the state's primary extractive industries, the Lesley collection is an important resource for examining the growth and direction of the state's economy and the relationship of science, industry, and the state. His correspondence, including letters written by and to him, also document the activities of both the First and Second Pennsylvania Geological Survey, the teaching of geology at the University of Pennsylvania, and the professional interests and relationships of natural scientists during the last half of the nineteenth century.
Lesley was in regular correspondence with most of the major figures in American geology, and particularly those with an interest in coal. The collection includes over 400 letters from Lesley's close friend Leo Lesqueureux, the Swiss-American paleobotanists who specialized in coal measure plants, but there is a substantive correspondence with James D. Dana, James F. Whitney, James Hall, Henry Darwin Rogers, Louis Agassiz, Arnold Guyot, David Dale Owen, and others. The collection is particularly strong in materials relating to the operation and results of the Second Pennsylvania Geological Survey.
Susan Lesley's correspondence is as interesting as Peter's. Her circle of friends included a number of progressive thinkers, many associated with the Transcendentalist and Unitarian communities in Boston (e.g. James Freeman Clarke, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Theodore Parker), and she corresponded as well with a number of prominent antislavery figures, including Theodore Dwight Weld, Samuel J. May, Frederick Douglass, and Maria Chapman. One of her closest friends and most regular correspondents was the writer and reformer Lydia Maria Child, from whom she received a total of 54 letters.
The Lesley Papers are divided into three series:
Series I. General Correspondence, 1826-1898 (29 boxes, 7.25 linear feet)
Series II. Correspondence with Joseph Lesley, 1850-1887 (2 boxes, 0.5 linear feet)
Series III. Notebooks, 1839-1896 (6 reels of microfilm)
Maps note
There are approximately 300 maps in this collection, generally small, and in journals and field notebooks. They tend to pertain to a discrete aspect of a geological problem. Realms of Gold, 26.
Related Archival Materials note
The papers of Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, held in the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College, contain approximately ten letters from her father.
The papers of Charles W. Ames (22 cu. feet, 1803-1986), son-in-law of Peter and Susan Lesley, are held at the Minnesota Historical Society.
The APS houses several maps made by Lesley, including a manuscript geological map of Wythe County, Virginia, and several printed maps produced by the Second Pennsylvania Geological Survey.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Charles Lesley Ames, 1942, and transferred by the Minnesota Historical Society, 1972. Letters to Joseph Lesley were the gift of Allen Lesley and Joseph Lesley, 1976. Six daguerreotypes of J. Peter Lesley and Susan Lesley were donated to the APS in 2000, along with an autobiography of Léo Lesquereux sent to Lesley. The Lesquereux autobiography is catalogued separately.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The Lesley Papers have been microfilmed as History of Science Film 12, reels 1-12
Biographical/Historical note
When J. Peter Lesley (1819-1903) graduated from the University of Pennsylvania in 1838, he intended for the Presbyterian ministry, but when ill health intervened, he was set off on a path that would make him one of the most influential geologists in 19th century Pennsylvania. In order to help rebuild his strength and restore his health, Lesley accepted an appointment with the first Pennsylvania Geological Survey under the direction of Henry Darwin Rogers and engaged in structural and stratigraphic work and topographical and geological mapping in the Pennsylvania anthracite belt. By 1841, he had recovered sufficiently to return to his divinity studies at Princeton Theological Seminary, but continued all the while to work for the Survey on a part time basis, mostly in preparing maps.
After a trip to Europe in 1844 to polish off his ministerial education, Lesley accepted a pulpit in rural central Pennsylvania, and moved three years later to take the helm of a Congregational church in Milton, Massachusetts. There he came into contact with a politically progressive, intellectually stimulating crowd that included Lydia Maria Child, James Freeman Clarke, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, and the fringes of the Transcendentalists and reformers. A young Unitarian member of this circle, Susan Inches Lyman, became Lesley's wife in February, 1849, and both shared their associates' progressive political and social vision.
As he had all along, Lesley continued to work on an occasional basis for the Geological Survey until 1852, when a long-standing conflict with Rogers over credit for field assistants led him to resign. That year marked an even more profound change in Lesley's life, as he also decided to leave the church and return home to Pennsylvania. Coinciding with the period of extraordinary expansion in the coal and rail industries in Pennsylvania, Lesley devoted himself fully to geological work. Employed by the Pennsylvania Railroad Company and other corporations, Lesley was an important cartographer - one of the first to employ contour lines to represent topography - and was an important writer and synthesizer of knowledge about the coal and iron regions. He is credited with some of the first systematic studies of coal, oil, and gas resources in the state.
Lesley's rising prestige in scientific circles led to his election to the American Philosophical Society in 1856, where he instilled himself in the Society's leadership, serving as librarian (1858-1885), secretary (1859-1887), and vice president (1887-1898). During his tenure as librarian, he introduced a new system of arranging books by subject, anticipating in some ways Melvil Dewey's system, but employing small spine labels arranged in the colors of the spectrum to represent the areas of knowledge. He was, as well, a charter member of the National Academy of Sciences in 1863.
Lured to the University of Pennsylvania as Professor of Mining in 1859, Lesley became a fixture there, too. Lesley's acquisition of a major collection of fossils, rocks, and minerals from James Hall, state geologist of New York, helped consolidate geology as a major subject of study at Penn. Lesley later became Professor of Geology and Mining Engineering and Dean of the Science Faculty, and in 1875, he was appointed Dean of the newly formed Towne Scientific School.
The continuing importance of the oil industry to Pennsylvania's economy led to calls for a second state Geological Survey, and for the duration of its existence, from 1874 to 1889, Lesley served as Director. An immense operation by the standards of the first Survey, at least, the second Survey was also immensely productive, issuing dozens of publications on the topography, geology, paleontology, and mineral resources of the state. He was in the midst of preparing a state-mandated final report for the Survey in 1893 when he suffered a complete breakdown. He never recovered.
Lesley died in 1903. One of his two daughters, Mary, married the prominent Minneapolis businessman, Charles W. Ames (1855-1921), and the other, Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown (1857-1944), became a well known artist, some of whose portraits hang in the APS.
African American History Note
The antislavery interests of J. Peter and Susan Lesley are reflected in letters from correspondents such as Lydia Maria Child, James Freeman Clarke, and Thomas Wentworth Higginson. The collection also includes a letter of Frederick Douglass (September 6, 1856) in which Douglass offers to assist Susan Lesley in locating the son of a "colored" friend of hers.
Early American History Note
J.P. Lesley was a prominent Pennsylvanian who became a leading geologist. This collection contains a range of materials that relate to his life. The content of the correspondence is not just scientific. Instead, subjects span a wide-range of topics, including European travel, the Civil War, politics, art, literature, personal affairs, and family matters. The papers also reflect Lesley wide-ranging scientific interests. Although a geologist, Lesley also dabbled in demographic studies, religion, and philology. A fair amount of the collection is from the 1850s and beyond. Much of this early correspondence is among family members, but some letters are from prominent reformers, such as Lydia Maria Child. Among the Lesley papers are poems, journals, and notebooks. Two boxes date from 1841 to 1851, which, notably, deal with the period before Lesley became a full-time geologist and professor at the University of Pennsylvania.
Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Barois, Charles; Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876; Child, Lydia Maria, 1802-1880; Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; Cope, E. D., (Edward Drinker), 1840-1897; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895; Desor, E. (Edouard), 1811-1882; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882; Flint, Austin; Frazer, John Fries, 1812-1872; Furness, Horace Howard, 1833-1912; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1822-1908; Guyot, A., (Arnold), 1807-1884; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Hale, Lucretia P., (Lucretia Peabody), 1820-1900; Hall, James; Hayden, F. V., (Ferdinand Vandeveer), 1829-1887; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911; King, Clarence, 1842-1901; Lesley, Joseph, 1831-1889; Lesley, Susan I., (Susan Inches), 1823-1904; Lesquereux, Leo, 1806-1889; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Lyman, Benjamin Smith, 1835-1920; M'Kim, J. Miller, (James Miller), 1810-1874; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Marsh, Othniel Charles, 1831-1899; McKinley, Alexander; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892; Peirce, Benjamin, 1809-1880; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866; Shaler, Nathaniel Southgate, 1841-1906; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874; Thomson, J. Edgar, (James Edgar), 1808-1874; Whitney, J. D. (Josiah Dwight), 1819-1896; Winsor, Henry; Wright, Chauncey,1830-1875.; Abolition, emancipation, freedom; Americans Abroad; Avesta; Biographies.; Cartography.; Charities -- United States.; Clippings.; Diaries.; Education--United States; Egypt--Antiquities.; Egyptian language--Writing, Hieroglyphic; Family Correspondence; France--Description and travel; Funeral rites and ceremonies--Egypt; General Correspondence; Geological Survey of Pennsylvania; Geology--Maps; Geology--Nova Scotia--Surveys; Geology--Pennsylvania; Germany--Description and travel; Hawaiian language; International Travel; Javanese language; Journals (notebooks); Literature; Literature, Arts, and Culture; Marriage and Family Life; Nova Scotia--Surveys; Obelisks; Paleontology--Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania--Surveys; Philology; Photographs; Poems; Scientific Data; Sketches.; Slavery -- United States.; Social conditions, social advocacy, social reform; Switzerland--Description and travel; Transcendentalism; Travel Narratives and Journals; Unitarianism; United States - History - Civil War, 1861-1865
- Series I. General correspondence, 1826-1898 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence of J. Peter Lesley and his wife, Susan, 1829-1898. The scientific content of the collection is significant. It contains abundant correspondence between Lesley and such prominent scientists as James Hall, Leo Lesquereux, Henry Darwin Rogers, and James Dwight Dana, but also geological notes, surveys, sketches and views on teaching, field work and mapping. The materials relating to the Second Geological Survey are particularly rich, including not only correspondence, but a four volume diary, 1874-1881, and four volumes of accounts relating to Lesley's direction of the Geological Survey of Pennsylvania, and including newspaper clippings, letters, and extracts from publications. The second volume is a "private" diary.
  Among many miscellaneous notebooks are Lesley's notes of a geological survey of the Pottsville District, 1851 (in the same volume is Benjamin Smith Lyman's "Levels of Survey near Llewellyn," 1862); his notes of a survey at Emigh's Gap; and Alexander McKinley's geological report book, 1839, for the Seven Mountains and Warrior's Ridge, Center County, Pennsylvania, accompanied by Lesley's final report, 1839-1940. Among the miscellaneous geological volumes are a dictionary of fossils found in Pennsylvania and a survey by Benjamin Smith Lyman of Converse and Panolt Leases, Glace Bay, Cape Breton Island.
  In addition, there are notebooks containing poems (1 v.), and four volumes of a journal kept on Lesley's ministerial tour of France, Germany, and Switzerland, 1844-1845. There are also some miscellaneous notes and essays on a diversity of topics including discussions of obelisks, the Zend-Avesta, European place names, Egyptian burial customs, lists of Hawaiian words, notes on Javanese and East Indian words and customs, religion and superstition, and archaeology.
  Both Peter and Susan Lesley maintained significant correspondences with major intellectual figures, including Lydia Maria Child, James Freeman Clarke, and Thomas Wentworth Higginson. Both commented on both the mundane and the major issues of the day, and Susan's correspondence, in particular, can be fascinating, including discussions of the abolition of slavery, educational reform, organized charity, Unitarianism, the Civil War, and implicitly and explicitly, a woman's role in society.
  - to J. Peter Lesley, 1826 June 17; Williston, P. (Box 1)
  - Poem: The Orphan, addressed to Elizabeth O. Lesley., 1829 March 4; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1832 August 9; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Elizabeth Lesley., 1832 August 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to "Dear Cousin E", 1834 March 20; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley]., 1834 August 27; Lesley, J. Peter and A. Lesley (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.]., 1834 May 29; Lesley, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1835 August 11; Lesley, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1836 August 8; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1836 August 23; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Susan [Inches Lyman]., [1837] Jan. 26; Colman, James F. (Box 1)
  - to, 1837 Feb. 3; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1837 April 17; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1837 July 20; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1837 August 22; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1837 Septem. 8; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Mrs. Lesley], 1837 Sept. 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1837 Sept. 14; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1837 Sept. 22; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - Thanks of the 2nd Presbyterian Church to J. Peter Lesley for the view of the church presented by him, [1838 April 5]; Hazard, Samuel (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1838 April 22; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1838 June 12; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1838 June 23; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 April 22; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. Lesley., 1839 April (?); Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Elizabeth Lesley, 1839 April 25; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. Sarah Allen., 1839 April 26; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley [Sr.], [1839 May 7]; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to H. B. Hall, 1839 May 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 May 15; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. S. E. Lesley., 1839 May 31; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 June 4; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to his brothers, William and Joseph [Lesley]., 1839 June 4; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. Sarah Allen., 1839 June 10; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - [J.Peter [Lesley] to Mrs. S. E. Lesley, [1839 June 10] (Box 1)
  - to Miss Elizabeth Lesley., 1839 June 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. Lesley, 1839 June 21; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. Anna Wilson, 1839 June 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 June 12; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 June 13; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to P[eter] Lesley, Sr., 1839 June 13; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to William and Joseph Lesley., 1839 June 18; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to H. D. Rogers., 1839 June 24; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to P[eter] Lesley, Sr., 1839 June 25; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Miss Eliz[abeth] Lesley., 1839 June 28; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. E. S. Lesley., 1839 July 1; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Miss E[lizabeth] Lesley., 1839 July 3; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [H.D. Rogers], 1839 July 6; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 July 20; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 July 22; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Henry Darwin Rogers, 1839 July 24; Lesley, J. Peter, Sr. (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 July 25; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 August 2; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to H. D. R[ogers]., 1839 August 5; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 August 10; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. Sarah Allen., 1839 August 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Aunt Anna Wilson., 1839 August 11; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to, 1839 August 14; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter] L[esley], Sr., 1839 August 21; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to H.D. Rogers, 1839 August 24; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 August 26; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 August 27; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - J. Peter Lesleyto Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 August 29 (Box 1)
  - J. Peter Lesleyto H. D. Rogers, 1839 August 29 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 August 31; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. S. E. Lesley, 1839 September 10; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Allen Lesley, 1839 Sept. 15, 17; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 September 23; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Jr. [salary on the survey], 1839 September 23; Petrikin, H. (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 September 26; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 October 5; Prevost, Lewis M. (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 October 8; Lyman, Mary (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 Oct. 10, 16; Lesley, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Jr., 1839 October 19; Stewart, William (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 October 28; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. S. E. Lesley, 1839 October 30; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 October 31; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1839 November 1; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 November 8; Lesley, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 November 11; Lesley, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1839 November 13; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 1)
  - to Mrs. [S.E.] Lesley., 1840 April 2; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Eliza.] Lesley, Sr., [1840 April 22]; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Peter] Lesley, Sr., 1840 April 27; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Prof. Ludlow., 1840 May 1; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Professor Ludlow., 1840 May 1; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Peter] Lesley, Sr., 1840 May 1; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to "John", 1840 May 4; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Mrs. S. E. Lesley, 1840 May 5; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to P[eter] Lesley, Jr., 1840 May 5; Ludlow, J. (Box 2)
  - to [Prof. Ludlow], 1840 May 20; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Mrs. Sarah Allen]., 1840 May 12; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1840 May 19; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Mrs. Anna Wilson., 1840 May 30; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1840 May 31; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Henry Lesley, 1840 June 4; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Mr. Peter Lesley, Sr., 1840 June 18; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to P[eter] Lesley, Sr., 1840 June 25; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to Peter Lesley, Sr., 1840 July 10; Lesley, Elizabeth (Box 2)
  - to Peter Lesley Sr., 1840 July 17; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)
  - to [Peter Lesley, Sr.], 1840 August 14; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903 (Box 2)